Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 12 -- Letters from Franklin 1733-1789 Mss.B.F85inventory12
American Philosophical Society
Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 12 -- Letters from Franklin
1733-1789
Mss.B.F85inventory12
American Philosophical Society
1.0 section
This is part of the large inventory for the Benjamin Franklin Papers (Mss B F85). For complete information concerning this collection, please view the Collection Description.
711 items
Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
- Letters from Benjamin Franklin
  - to [Mrs.] Deborah Franklin., 1733 August 30; D.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Scope and Contents note
    Power of attorney to Deborah Franklin.
  - to ----- Corin., 1738 December 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Order for a pair of leather breeches to be charged to his account.
  - to James Parker., 1741 February 20; D.S. James Parker, B[enjamin] Franklin. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Articles of agreement for carrying on the business of printing in the City of New York.
    Bibliography
    (Printed in the Proceedings of the Massachusetts Historical Society, 2d Ser., XVI, 186.)
  - to -----, -----., [1744 March.]?; A. Dr. of L. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    When he compares the Governor's Message to the House [in relation to the expedition against Cape Breton] with his private conversation cannot but admire at his insincerity, nor can be justify the Assembly from disingenuity in their answer. In short Governor [George Thomas] and the Assembly have been acting a farce and playing tricks to amuse the world. Abstract of the debate in the Assembly on the Governor's Message.
    (Incomplete.)
    General note
    see Also under 1766, P 464.
    [Notes on Assembly debates]
  - A Drinking Song., [1745.]; A. Dr. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - The Trade of Province of 40,000 Inhabitants., [1745.]; A. Dr. of Diss. 6p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Memorandum., [1746.]; A. Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    That Sally [Franklin] was inoculated April 18, 1746.
  - to [John Franklin]., 1747 August 6; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Glad to hear of Mr. [George] Whitefield's safe arrival. Received a letter from Mr. [Joseph] Dowse requesting an explanatiion of Dr. Franklin's dissatisfaction with Mrs. Steel(e); his reply and advice to his brother and sister regarding the affair.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, II, 316).
  - to Cadwallader Colden., 1747 August 6; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Franklin's opinion of the inertia of matter. Is glad to hear that Mr. Colden will proceed with the electrical experiments, and is satisfied that there are workmen in America who can make the apparatus; if Mr. Colden is satisfied to have it made here, he will oversee the work Mr. [James] Logan is satisfied that some of the faults he formerly objected to in Colden's article on fluxions, are his own.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 93; Bigelow, II, 103; Smyth, II, 322).
  - to -----, -----., [1747?]; A.L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Concerning the Articles of Association for the defense of the Province [of Pennsylvania].
    (Final part missing.)
  - Benjamin Franklin's Will., 1750 June 22; A.D.S. and witnessed. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    (Mutilated.)
  - to -----, -----., A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Relative to the conductivity of glass.
    (First part missing.)
  - to -----, -----., [1750.]; A. Dr. of L. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Description of a magic circle.
  - Plan for a Mortgage Association., [1750.]; A. Dr. of Mem. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - to -----, -----., [1757-1775]; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Recommends arbitration rather than a law-suit to collect a debt, concerning which he has been consulted.
  - To Rev. Mr. ----., 1766 September; A Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    If the venerable society shall appoint Mr. [Elihu] Spencer to the mission of Spotswood, in New Jersey, he will recommend him to the Governor of that Province. Rev. [William] Sturgeon, of Philadelphia, wrote to him that his health is so much on a decline, as to oblige him to retire into the country, and that he should think himself happy if the Society woudl appoint him to succeed Mr. [Colin] Campbel[l] at Burlington. Thinks Trenton, if vacant, would suit him.
  - to Cadwallader Colden., 1752 April 23; A. Dr. of L.S. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Regarding the improper distinction of Els. per se and non-Els., and the use of the terms conductors and non-conductors. Experiments and observations in electricity. Glad Mr. Colden's article on the Principles of Action in Matter, with the explanations will soon appear. Thanks him for communicating his Illustration of the Theorem of Light. Dr. Franklin's Theory of Light. Glad to hear of the sucess of poke weed as a cure for cancer.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, V, 283; Bigelow, II, 251; Smyth, III, 82).
  - to John Perkins., 1753 February 4; A. Dr. of L.S. 15p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    An apology for not answering sooner. Idea and illustration of a waterspout; its relation to a whirlwind.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 145: Bigelow, II, 267; Smyth, III, 107).
  - to Jared Eliot., 1753 May 3; A. Dr. of L.S. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Observations relative to water, air, trade-winds, etc.
    (Read before the Royal Society, November 4, 1756.)
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 174; Smyth, III, 129).
  - to Joseph Huey., 1753 June 6; A. Dr. of L. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Glad to hear of his improved health. Franklin's notion of Good Works—works of kindness, charity, mercy, and public spirit [concluding lines torn out].
    Printed in Works (Bigelow, II, 459; Smyth, III, 143.)
  - to -----, -----., 1753 July 12; A. L. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Account of a house struck by lightning. Course of the lightning and observations on its effects.
  - to W[illia]m Franklin, 1753 July 23; A.Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Glad to hear that he has taken a circumstantial account of the appearance at Trumble's house; which is sufficient to establish his new hypothesis of the direction of lightning. Received a pane of glass and a letter from Mr. [Ebenezer] Kinnersley mentioning his suspicions that the stoke was upwards. Wrote Mr. K. a short account of the experiment he made before he left home, and refers him to William Franklin for the explanation according to the new hypothesis. Expects to set out for home next Monday.
    P. S. Encloses a letter from William Franklin's uncle with a power of attorney, and desires him to attack for Franklin and Williams, Grant's right to Pitt's Walnut Street land by virtue of his mortgage.
    Printed, in part, in Works (Smyth, III, 147).
  - to Cadwallader Colden., 1753 November 19; A.Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    An answer to observations by Mr. Colden upon the letter from Dr. Franklin of May, 3, 1753, to Jared Eliot. (Read at the Royal Society, Nov. 4, 1756.)
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 180; Smyth, III, 186).
  - Conferences with Indians at Carlisle in September, 1753., A. Mem. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Draught of the plan of Union Proposed at Albany., 1754 July 9; Mem. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Influence of the French among the Indians; their design to surround the British Colonies. Rules for governing the Grand Council and powers to be entrusted to that body.
    (Many pages missing.)
    Printed in O'Calloghan, Doc. Hist. of New York, II, 608-609 and 613-614.
  - to [Mrs. Deborah Frankliln], 1754; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Presents his duty to her mother and love to the children and to all his friends.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin., 1775 April 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philiadelphia. Annapolis
    Arrived last night. Shall not return by the same road with the company, but will go round by Winchester, and so to Carlisle in order to settle the posts which the Assembly agreed to support for a year between the Camp and Philadelphia.
  - Memorandum., 1755 April; A. Mem. 5p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Lancaster
    Benjamin Franklin's accounts in the matter of the hiring of wagons for the transportation of supplies for General Braddock's army.
  - Memorandum., [1775? April.]; [1748 March 21]; Mem. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Proposal that the Managers of the Lottery be applied to arrange for defense of the Colony of Pennsylvania against the French and Indians on the Coast and Frontier. Outline of plans for the defense.
  - to [William] Johnson, 1755 October 16; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Settled Col. [William] Hunter's account. Encloses a copy of General [William] Shirley's warrant to [Sir William] Johnson for such payments as the wagon affair may require. Hopes that when Johnson and Shirley meet some method will be found of transferring the cash for the payment of those poor people, without risk or trouble.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, III, 289).
  - to [William] Hunter., 1755 October 16; A. Dr. of L. S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Could not avoid meeting the Assembly who are now sitting; will await his arrival to settle their money accounts and make measures relating to the wagon affair. General [William] Shirley sent his Warrant to Mr. [Sir William] Johnson to pay Franklin such sums as are necessary to settle the wagon accounts.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, III, 290).
  - to General [William] Shirley., 1755 October 23; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Thanks him for the orders for the payment of the wagon owners. Cannot see the papers to which he is referred because of the absence of the Governor. Sorry he cannot see him at New York.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 55; Bigelow, II, 418; Smyth, III, 290).
  - to Captain [William] Shirley., 1755 October 23; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Received his favor of the 1st with discharges of Ewins and Rieger; will take care to observe the directions relating to them.
  - to [Peter] Collinson., 1755 October 25; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Hopes he received the bill for £75 when he wrote for one of Mr. [John] Smeaton's new air pumps for the Academy; sends a bill for £30 with a list of some philosophical implements, which he begs him to send, insured. News just arrived that eight families near Shamokin were cut off last week by Indians. The people on the frontier will be furnished with arms and ammunition. Hopes to be home when the next Assembly meets.
  - to Richard Partridge., 1755 October 25; L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Extract from preceding letter.
    (Copy.)
  - to [Richard] Partridge., 1755 October 25; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    The new Assembly chose Mr. Partridge and Mr. [Robert] Charles as their agents for the ensuing year. A considerable sum is subscribed for the supply for the troops, on the frontier of New York, etc., during the winter, with warm waistcoats, etc. The Indians last week cut off eight families; 600 arms have been purchased for the people of the frontier. Heard that a petition will be sent to the King against the Assembly. Hopes Parliament will establish a union of the Colonies for the common defence.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, III, 292).
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1755 December 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Easton
    Glad the companies are forming in town and choosing their officers. Marched Aston's and Trump's companies over the mountains after many difficulties. Waiting for supplies.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 102; Bigelow, II, 445; Smyth, III, 320).
  - Address., [1755 ?]; Ms. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia. Easton
    Concerning the assignment of the Dock Ward and other Militia Companies. (Incomplete.)
  - to -----. -----., 1755; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Asserts that it is false that few people seem inclined to muster arms under the present military laws. States that nine companies of the Philadelphia regiment of foot under Col. Franklin, consisting of about 1000 men, appeared in arms, being mustered by the officers commissioned in pursuance of the law. States that the German people made a considerable part of the body.
  - Memorandum., [1755?]; A. Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    List of necessaries wanted for the hospital of the 1st Battalion of the Royal American Regiment at Philadelphia.
  - to ----- Harris., 1755; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Congratulations on the birth of a daughter. Sends his blessing to the little stranger and desires to know her name.
  - Memorandum., [1755.]; A. Mem. 7p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Relating to the militia; to the establishing of a Post of Tioga, and to the abvisability of concerting with New York and Massachusetts as to the raising of troops; eclipses; physician's fees; amount of linen, etc.
  - to Mrs. Franklin, Deborah. Philadelphia., 1756 January 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Bethlehem
    Thinks the line of forts will be finished in a fortnight or three weeks. will then make a trip to Philadelphia to send away the lottery tickets and pay off the prizes.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 104; Bigelow, II, 447; Smyth, III, 323).
  - to Mrs. Deborah Franklin, Philadelphia., 1756 March 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Frederictown
    Excepts to sail that day. Peter [his servant] was taken ill but is almost well again. Informs her if she wants money to present one of the two orders he left with her to Mr. Cha[rle]s Norris. Enjoins her to be careful of her accounts, particularly about the lottery affairs. If there is peace shall probably not come home so soon as he purposed.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 115; Bigelow, II, 457; Smyth, III, 331).
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1756 March 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Williamsburg
    Account of his journey; may return to New York with Colonel [William] Hunter and his lady in the Man-of-War.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 116; Bigelow, II, 458; Smyth, III, 332).
  - to [Mrs. Deborah Franklin.], 1756 [April 5]; A.L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Arrived at Col. [William] Hunter's, near Hampton, where he was received in the most obliging manner. Mr. Hunter is not ill but thin. Condition of the place at the time. Uncertain as to the time he may return or the way he shall take back. Asks her to deliver the money, belonging to Col. Hunter, to Mr. Nelson when he calls for it, taking his receipt. (First par missing.)
  - to Mrs. Deborah Franklin., 1756; A.L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Continues well. Arrived with Mr. [William] Hunter yesterday. Have almost finished their business together. (Fragment.)
  - Physical and Meteorological Observations, Conjectures and Suppositions., 1756 [May ?]; [1751 ?]; Diss. Ms. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Read at the Royal Society, June 3, 1756.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 127; Smyth, III, 175).
  - to T[homas] Pownall., 1756 August 19; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Encloses a copy of the late conference at Easton; the Indians are preparing to continue the war. Opinion of Sir William Johnson's step to procure peace with the Six Nations. If Lord Loudoun would order the recruits to the frontier, they would be of great assistance to the inhabitants.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 121; Bigelow, II, 468; Smyth, III, 341).
  - Memorandum., [1756?]; A. Dr. of Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Events leading up to the French and Indian War arranged in chronological order.
  - to General William Shirley, [1756.]; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Is represented at home as an opposer of Government and disaffected to the King's service. Since he is acquainted with what zeal he served Gen. [Edward] Braddock and also with his readiness to assist his forces by affecting the grant from the Asembly for £10,000 in provisions and clothing; he desires him to mention these things in a letter to him that he may be at liberty to communicate it to Sir Everard Fawkener,and thus remove any impressions to his disadvantage.
  - to General William Shirley, [1756.]; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Like the preceding with but slight change of wording. Acquaints him of what part he took in the grant and that he actually subscribed three tenths of the whole for which he is not yet reimbursed.
  - to [Robert] Charles., 1757 February 1; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Sends him copies of last year's votes, and other valuable papers. It is estimated that £125,000 is necessary to defend the Province for one year; this large sum cannot be raised and three-fourths of the troops must be disbanded. The House has asked Mr. [Isaac] Norris and Dr. Franklin to go to England to assist in getting these matters settled.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 127; Bigelow, II, 483; Smyth, III, 367).
  - to [Richard] Partridge, 1757 February.; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Would have written a long letter but the House desired the Speaker and him to go immediately home and settle the differences with the Proprietors; it is possible that one of them will soon have the pleasure of seeing and conferring with him on their affairs.
  - to [William] Dunlap, 1757 April 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Appoints him postmaster of Philadelphia during his absence; office is not be removed from his house without his consent. Tells him to pay attention to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin's advice. Is to retain 10 per cent commission. (Torn).
    Printed in Works (Bigelow, II, 496).
  - to Deborah Franklin, 1757 April 4; D.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Power of attorney.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, 1757 April 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia, Trenton
    On his journey to New York where he is to take passage to England.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 131; Bigelow, II, 497; Smyth, III, 378).
  - to Samuel Hazard, 1757 April 11; L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Regarding the misunderstanding between them relative to the prize-money and the Academy tickets.
  - to Dr. John Lining, 1757 April 14; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. New York
    A disquisition on heat and cold. (First part missing.)
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 203; Bigelow, II, 498; Smyth, III, 383).
  - to Dr. [Alexander] Garden, 1757 April 14; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, New York
    Is about to embark for London; refers him to his article on fire written to Dr. Lining. Introduces Colonel [Henry] Bouquet.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, III, 381).
  - to Colonel [Henry] Bouquet., 1757 April 14; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. New York
    Recommends him to an ingenious physician in Charlestown who knows the rule of making cool, weak, refreshing punch. Prays that he has a pleasant voyage.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, III, 382.)
  - to James Parker, 1757 April 22; A.L.S. [Benjamin] Franklin and [William] Hunter. 7p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Instructions for him as Comptroller of the General Post-Office during Mr. [Benjamin] Franklin's absence.
  - to Whom it May Concern., 1757 April 22; A. Dr. by Franklin of D.S. [Benjamin] Franklin and [Wiliam] Hunder. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Commission of James Parker as their Agent and Comptroller of the Post-Offices of North America.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1757 April 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. New York
    Is determined against going in the first pacquet. Asks her to send him the Indian sealskin hussiff with all the things that were in it, the Indian lady's gut-cambric, and one or two books on the game of chess.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, III, 392).
  - to [Peter Franklin?], 1757 May 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Woodbridge, New Jersey
    Has already waited six weeks for the sailing of the pacquet and still does not know when she is likely to sail; will not meddle with his paper currency sinice he always loses by it; his wife is with him, but Billy and Sally [Franklin] are in New York.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Woodbridge, [N. J.], 1757 May 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. New York
    Delayed at New York. Dined with Lord Loudoun; French fleet reported to be cruising off the coast. May stay at Woodbridge until the pacquet sails, and, while there, try to finish his work. (Mutilated.)
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 135; Bigelow, II, 509; Smyth, III, 395).
  - to Isaac Norris., 1757 May 30; A.Dr. of L.S. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin. New York
    Delays in sailing. Interview with Lord [Loudoun] respecting the pay to servants enlisted in the army.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 138; Bigelow, II, 512; Smyth, III, 397).
  - to [Mrs. Deborah Franklin]., 1757 June 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. New York
    Will go on board the next day. Hopes Sally [Franklin] will be obedient and mind her learning and improvement.
    (Multilated.)
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 145; Bigelow, II, 519; Smyth, III, 405).
  - to --------- --------., [1757?] June 5; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. New York
    Is at length going abroad; it is said the fleet will sail to-morrow, but this cannot be depended upon.
  - to Mrs. Deborah Franklin. Philadelphia., 1757 July 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    His arrival in London.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 149; Bigelow, II, 520; Smyth, III, 419).
  - to Dr. [John] Fothergill., [1757. October.] Tuesday morning; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Took the powder he prescribed and had a good night's rest. Had no headache in the morning and therefore did not cup. Had, however, a giddiness and swimming in his head which, whenever he rises or turns suddenly, makes him stagger; hears a humming noise in his head and sees faint twinkling lights. Asks for his advice.
  - to [Mrs. Deborah Franklin]., 1757 November 22; A.L. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    His long illness. Will entertain Mr. [Peter] Collinson and Dr. [John] Fothergill with her account of Tedynskung's visit. Glad Sally [Franklin] went to Elizabethtown. General [William] Shirley's affairs in an uncertain state and he (Gen. S.) is endeavoring to obtain an enquiry into his conduct. Tells her not to be troubled about reports spread by his enemies about him; should he not be able to do his country any good; he will at least take care not to do it any harm. The agrecable conversation he meets with among men of learning and the notice taken of him by persons of distinction, are the principal things that soothe him during this painful absence from his family and friends; yet those would not detain him another week if he had not other inducements; duty to his country and hopes of being able to do it some service.
    (Part missing.)
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 149; Bigelow, II, 521; Smyth, III, 429).
  - to [Mrs. Deborah Franklin]., 1758 February 19; A.L.S. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Death of his friend [William] Parsons. Hackney coaches in London; London one great smoky house. His health. Account of various articles he sent her.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 163; Bigelow, III, 5; Smyth, III, 430).
  - to [Mrs. Deborah Franklin]., 1758 June 10; A.L.S. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Presents. Domestic concerns. Electric bells. Prudent for her not to engage in Party disputes. The Proprietors have determined to discard Governor [William] Denny on account of his conduct. Governorship offered to a certain Mr. Graves, who declined to accept it.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VII, 167; Bigelow, III, 12; Smyth, III, 438).